我背后那片地方 我愿称之为宇宙中心
if you look right behind me you'll see the center of the universe
因为那是NASA的喷气推进实验室(JPL)
and the reason it's called the center of the universe is because that's NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory
我们在太阳系甚至以外发射的所有轨道器、探测器、航天器
and all of the orbiters, probes and spacecraft we've sent out into the solar system and beyond
它们的数据都会汇总到这里进行处理
send all their signals right back here to be processed
原视频发表于2021年2月15日 毅力号着陆前三天
过几天下一辆火星车毅力号着陆的时候就更能体现这一点了
and that will never be more apparent than in a few days when the next Mars rover named Perseverance
在向着那个红色星球飞行了七个月后
concludes its seven month journey to our neighboring red planet mars
它将在恐怖七分钟内进行全自动导航
autonomously navigating itself for a terrifying seven minutes
从15倍子弹速度到每小时仅3英里(大约1.34米每秒)的软着陆
traveling from 15 times the speed of a bullet to a gentle 3 mph touchdown
全程都会传回关键数据并直播
all while live streaming the key data the whole way down
了解我的粉丝们可能知道我到这就像到家一样
and as many of you know for me this is like coming home
因为很久以前我开始做YouTuber的时候我在这里天天上班上了九年
because long before i started making youtube videos i came here to work every day for nine years
其中七年的时候我在造上一辆火星车 名字叫好奇号
seven of which we're working on the last rover we sent to mars named Curiosity
所以今天我要和我的老朋友们叙叙旧 带你们近距离看看真正的火星车
so today we're gonna talk to some of my old friends and see the actual rover up close
我要带你们快速了解火星车着陆相关的内容
as i bring you up to speed on everything you need to know about this rover landing
因为我敢肯定当你们知道要发生什么 以及我们为此都付出过什么以后
because once you have an overview of what's gonna happen and what it even took to get us to this point
你们绝对像我一样对这样历史性的着陆心潮澎湃
i feel certain you're gonna feel just as pumped about this historic landing as i am
为此 我们将了解这辆火星车的"谁 什么 为什么去 去哪 怎么去"
and to accomplish that, we're gonna talk about the who what why where and how of this rover
我们先讲去哪和为什么要去
we'll start with the why and the where we're going
35亿年前火星和地球其实非常相似
3.5 billion years ago earth and Mars were pretty similar
表面都有液态水 都有能屏蔽太阳辐射的电磁场
both had liquid water on the surface and both were protected from the sun's radiation with magnetic fields
于是问题来了 如果当时地球上出现了生命
and so it begs the question if life first developed on Earth at that time
那火星上会出现吗？
could it have also developed on Mars?
这是数十亿年前火星上的一个巨大湖泊 杰泽罗陨石坑
so this is a massive lake in Jezero Crater billions of years ago
而这是它现在的样子
and this is it now
这是毅力号着陆的地点 一个和太浩湖差不多大的古代湖泊的湖底
this is where Perseverance is landing, the bottom of an ancient lake the size of Lake Tahoe
因为参考地球的话 科学家们相信在流水的底部
because using Earth as a guide at the base of a river of fresh water is where scientists believe
有最高概率能发现火星过去的古生物存在证据
we have the best chance of finding evidence of past biological life on Mars
所以多亏了毅力号
so thanks to Perseverance
我们可能即将迎来第一次发现地球外实际生命的伟大时刻
we could be on the verge of the monumental first discovery of actual life outside our planet
而且我们通过着陆点范围 还能发现NASA的科技水平是如何步步前进的
and being able to pinpoint a landing spot this tight shows how NASA is constantly advancing its technologies
同比例在这放个佛罗里达州 之后几个椭圆会显示过去几次任务的预定着陆范围
with florida for scale here's an oval showing the uncertainty of the landing spot for previous missions
分别是1997年探路者号、2008年凤凰号、2012年好奇号和现在的毅力号
Pathfinder in 1997, and then Phoenix in 2008, Curiosity in 2012, and now Perseverance
能更加精确的着陆可以让你有更多有意义的着陆点选择
being able to shrink down a landing target just gives you way more options of interesting places to land
而且着陆后火星车驶向实际科学勘探区也更快
plus once you do land and start driving towards the actual science location
节省一年甚至更长的行驶时间
it can shave off a year or more of drive time
如此研究火星不但能帮助我们了解地球的过去和将来
not only does studying Mars like this help us understand earth's past and future
还能让火星车作为我们的先锋侦察兵
but the rovers we're sending are the advanced scouts
在火星表面采集数据做下记录并把数据传回地球
taking data and notes for us on the ground and sending all the info back to Earth
他们还会测试一项新技术 我稍后会讲
they're also testing some new technologies which I'll cover in a second
人类在不远的将来登陆火星后使用这项新技术
that humans will need to use when we're exploring the planet ourselves in the very near future
毕竟第一个登上火星的人现在已经出生了
because the first person to set foot on Mars is alive right now
而TA很可能是你
and it could be YOU
如果连这都没让你激动
and if none of that gets your heart pumping
你还是满脸“就这?连地球那点破事都解决不好还搁那费时费力探索太阳系?”
and you're like "but mark, why would we spend resources and time exploring the solar system
when we still have big issues here on this earth we haven't solved?"
av25441370
我在另一个视频里解答了这个问题 给出了我们不能不花钱探索宇宙的五个原因
I tackled that exact question giving five reasons we can't afford not to invest in space in another video
你可以看完这个视频后去看看那个
you can watch after this one
这就是“去哪”和“为什么去”
so that's the where and the why
接下来我们说怎么去
now let's talk about how we're going to do all that
因为高能要来了
because this is where it gets really wild
隆重介绍——毅力号！
Meet PERSEVERANCE!
其实我每月更新的视频每个都会提前一年准备
and i should mention i have my monthly videos all planned out about a year in advance
因此这个视频在一年前我就知道我必须飞到这里亲自来看看火星车
which is why exactly this time last year i knew for this video i needed to fly down to check out the rover
还要赶在它被运到佛罗里达发射之前
right before it got shipped off to florida to be launched
但在我看火星车之前 我先去看了看Ben 他是我以前的老板
but before i checked out the rover i first stopped in to see Ben who was my old boss
应该就是天空起重机吧？
我以前在这的时候 他的小团队设计了把火星车降到地面上的反推组件
when i was here he was leading a small team that designed the jet pack that lowered the rover to the ground
但我现在听说他已经牛逼到管四百来人了
but now i heard he's all fancy in charge of like 400 people
所以我想去看看他到底变化有多大
so i wanted to get a sense of how things had changed for him
这附近每个人你都能使唤吗？比如这人 你能随便使唤他吗？
so anyone we see walk by you can like boss them around, about this guy right here, you can boss him around?
满脸写着开心
对 我能随便使唤他
yeah i can boss him around
行吧 牛逼 咱们继续
Okay cool ... go on
我们先在这里把玩了一些之前任务里的示例组件
we first geeked out for a bit over a bunch of examples of parts from previous space missions
这满墙零件的画面很好的说明了为什么在JPL工作太帅了
and a hardware wall like this is just a great illustration of what makes JPL such a cool place to work
GRAIL: Gravity Recovery and Interior Laboratory NASA的一对月球探测器
啊这个是我设计的 我和Andy在GRAIL项目上做的
actually I designed this, this is my hardware from GRAIL with Andy
这个还挺巧妙的 这些弯曲的部分是为了应对温度的变化
this was cool because you got these like flexures for like temperature variation
不是为了好看 而是真的为了想办法实现某些功能
so this isn't just for show this is like literally when you're trying to figure out a way to do things
这些都是之前任务里的样例吗？
these are examples of how it's been done before, right?
对 而且这里有很多是反面教材
right and a lot of these are made by examples of this is the way you shouldn't do
-靠 所以我设计的零件…  -所以你的零件摆在这里了 懂了吧
-oh so that's why my hardware  -that's why your hardware's up there, right?
之后我们去看了火星车 见到了我的朋友Emily
after that we headed down to check out the rover and meet up with my friend Emily
但在看火星车之前我们必须全副武装
but before we could just go in and see it we had to get suited up
因为火星车是要去寻找生命迹象的
because the rover is looking for signs of biological life
可不能还没到火星呢就把样品污染了
and we don't want to contaminate our samples before we even arrive
所以穿衣服然后吹风就要花上一阵
so a bunny suit and air shower can go a long way
Emily是探测器下降级和巡航级的组装主管
Emily by the way was the vehicle assembly lead for the descent and cruise stages
责任非常重
which is a big responsibility
-这就是火星车了  -要上火星的那个 12个月后它就在火星上了
-this is the rover  -the flight rover, it will be on Mars 12 months from now
离近了看感觉它好复杂啊
it's so complex when you come up and get this close
实际上毅力号是迄今为止人类送到其他星球上的最复杂的物体了
in fact Perseverance is the most complex thing humans have ever built and sent to another planet
它装有激光 X光 雷达 19台相机 还有核电池
it's got laser x-ray and radar capabilities plus 19 cameras and a nuclear-powered battery system for energy
可能看上去和上一辆火星车好奇号很像
and while it might look pretty similar to the past rover Curiosity
但两者的科学仪器是完全不同的 因为科学目标有所改变
all the science instruments are completely different because the science objectives have changed
这次最大的不同是钻头不再是单纯打碎石头然后在火星车上研究
the most notable difference is this time the drill isn't there just to create rock dust to study on the rover
毅力号有一个中空的钻头 可以抽取一段粉笔大小的岩石样本
Perseverance has a hollow drill bit to core out a chunk of rock the size of a piece of chalk
还能打包起来留下43个不同的样品
and then package it up and leave behind 43 separate samples
用于未来任务收集起来并送回地球
for a future mission to collect and send back to Earth
这样 我们就能用地球上的先进设备研究样本上生命曾经存在的证据了
that way we could study the samples for those past signs of life
而这样的检测设备火星车根本放不下
using the most state-of-the-art instruments on earth that we could never fit on a rover
因此 为了获取那段粉笔大小的岩石样品
so then to capture that chalk size rock sample
这次毅力号不但在外侧有机械臂 在内部也有一个
not only is there an arm on the outside but this time there's one on the inside too
它是一个小型机械手 可以操控样品管
it is a miniature robot arm inside the body of the rover that manipulates the sample tube
-这就是其中一个样品管  -哇
-and there's one right here  -wow
-这就是要留在火星上的?  -没错
-and so is this what you leave behind?  -exactly
-我能说这有点像火星车在拉臭臭吗?  -没错!  -好
-is it fair to say this is like the poop of the rover?  -exactly  -okay
-你觉得这比喻咋样?我看他们之前好像不太喜欢  -好啊
-do you like that analogy? because they didn't like it earlier  -yeah
我们的确会说火星车要在火星表面把样品“拉”出去
we do like to say that the rover's gonna poop out the sample on the surface
你看 这比喻很不错啊
see that's a good analogy
因此 毅力号是实打实的火星表面采样返回任务的第一步
so Perseverance is really only the first leg of returning a piece of Mars to earth
未来几次任务用我的话说就是 拉臭臭-捡臭臭-射！
future missions will complete what i like to call the poop scoop and shoot maneuver
也就是之前提到的“拉臭臭-捡臭臭-射”流程
这是我的朋友Liz 她负责样品采集系统的所有测试工作
this is my friend Liz by the way and she's in charge of all the testing for the sample retrieval system
我们做的事情前无古人 所以必须要进行测试
we're doing things that nobody else does so we have to test it
她在一个密封舱内进行了各种不同构型的测试
so she tests all sorts of different configurations in a chamber
舱内可以模拟极端温度和压力 保证设备在火星上能正常工作
that recreates the extreme temperatures and pressures to make sure it will function on Mars
因为一旦发射到太空就变成泼出去的水了 你不可能上去维修它
because once you send something to space it's gone and you can't exactly fix it
所以必须要进行测试 这也是为什么测试在JPL是非常重要的事情
so it just has to work which is why testing is such a big deal here at JPL
我的朋友Matt提到了另一种测试方法
my buddy Matt here mentioned another way this is done
我们会造两艘航天器 一个去火星 一个留在地球进行测试
so we build two spacecraft one that goes to Mars and one that we keep here on earth to test
这是好奇号的复制品 它的双胞胎现在就在火星上跑
and this is an exact replica of curiosity who's driving around on Mars right now
我们用手边这辆测试行驶避障 翻越碎石的能力
and then we use this one to test driving around obstacles and driving over rocks
而他的确很懂翻越碎石这些事
and he knows a thing or two about driving over rocks
因为他同时是机遇号和好奇号的“司机”
because he was a rover driver for both opportunity and curiosity
这人算是这个星球上驾驶另一个星球上的车的 可能仅有的40人吧
this guy is like one of maybe 40 people in the world who has driven a vehicle on another planet
真的老牛逼了
which is kind of a big deal
毅力号另一个亮点是它底部还有一个折叠无人直升机 机智号
and so a few more cool things about Perseverance are that it has a mini helicopter drone
stowed away on its underbelly named ingenuity
这将是人类首次在其他星球上的有动力飞行
this will be mankind's first powered flight on another planet
有点像当年的莱特兄弟
which sort of makes this a Wright Brother's moment
火星车和无人机会互相拍一些好看的照片
the rover and the drone will get great footage of each other
当然我们主要目的是用来测试 未来我们可以用它来探测地形
but we're mainly testing it out so that in the future we might use drones to scout out terrain for us
或者去难以到达的地方采集样品
or get samples from hard to reach locations
或者用无人机集群为人类从一个地方到另一个地方运货
or you could have swarms of drones carrying materials for humans from one site to another
MOXIE: Mars Oxygen In-Situ Resource Utilization Experiment  火星氧气原位资源利用(ISRU)实验仪
毅力号还有一个叫MOXIE的设备 基本上相当于一个机械树
Perseverance is also testing out a new instrument called MOXIE that basically amounts to a mechanical tree
功能是将二氧化碳转换成氧气
because its function is to convert co2 into oxygen
未来可用于人类的呼吸 作为火箭的燃料
which future explorers will need to breathe and for rocket fuel
火星车在这间无尘室内已经呆了一年半了
the rover has been in this clean room for about a year and a half
最开始只是一堆框架 零件
starting as just a chassis just the skeleton
之后一个又一个的工程师团队轮流来这里
and then all the teams and engineers have been taking turns coming down
组装各自的组件直到完成
and building up their part until it's done
实际上我就是在这里设计了好奇号上的硬件 一呆就是三年半
in fact i was in that exact position on curiosity designing my hardware for about three and a half years
然后在这个无尘室内测试并安装到火星车上
and when it was all tested and complete integrating it on the rover right here in this room
然后就是又一个三年半 我之前提到过了
and then for the other three and a half years like i mentioned before
我和Ben在一个小团队里研发下降级的反推组件
i was working with ben on a small team of engineers on the jetpack descent stage
到现在我们讲了“去哪”和“为什么去”
so now we've covered the where and the why we're going
以及用那辆火星车“怎么做”
also the how we're gonna do all that with the rover
接下来我们讲讲“会发生什么”
now let's talk about the what
这周四它着陆时会发生什么 你会看到什么
for what's gonna happen this Thursday when it lands and what you should expect to see
约每小时77480公里 相对太阳
当我制作这期视频的时候 航天器正以每小时48144英里的速度向火星滑行
as i edit this video the spacecraft is gliding toward Mars at a cool 48,144 mph
有多快呢？有这么快
how fast is that? it's this fast
译注：！！！前方画面会有一次全屏白色频闪 请做好准备！！！
它是子弹速度的15倍
it's 15 times faster than a bullet
它会在接下来屏幕闪烁的一瞬间飞跃100个橄榄球场
it's traveling the length of 100 soccer fields in exactly this long
它还会以这样的轨迹飞行到周四的历史性时刻
and it will keep on that trajectory until the big moment on thursday
届时它将开始进入火星大气、下降、着陆 简称EDL
when it starts its entry descent and landing or EDL
这个过程也叫恐怖7分钟
it's also known as the seven minutes of tear
因为从到达火星大气顶部到着陆火星 一共只有7分钟
because we've literally got seven minutes to get from the top of the atmosphere to the surface of Mars
每小时13000英里≈每小时21000公里
速度从每小时13000英里减速到0 一切流程和时机都必须做到完美
going from 13,000 mph to 0 in perfect sequence and perfect timing
航天器完全要靠自己完成 没有任何地球的帮助
and the spacecraft has to do it all on its own with no help from us on earth
当它进入上层大气
when it first hits the upper atmosphere
剧烈的摩擦会让防热大底发光发热 就像太阳表面一样
the friction causes the heat shield to start glowing like the surface of the sun
与此同时推进器还会进行调整从而瞄准预定着陆点
all the while thrusters are firing to steer and adjust its course towards the target location
这样的气动减速可以消耗99%的能量
and that aero-breaking gets rid of 99 of the energy
之后为了那剩余的1% 我们会打开超音速降落伞
so for the last one percent we deploy a supersonic parachute
然后像打开镜头盖一样抛掉防热大底
then we've got to pop off the heat shield we no longer need like removing a lens cap
这样雷达就能看清地面了
so the radar can start viewing the ground
但即使有了降落伞 速度还是高达每小时200英里 对于着陆来说太快了
每小时200英里≈每小时320公里
but even with the parachute it's still traveling 200 miles per hour which is way too fast to land
所以我们之后要抛掉后盖 点燃火箭发动机
and so that's where we cut loose of the back shell and fire the rockets
但这样的造型还是不能着陆
but we can't quite land in this configuration
因为火箭尾焰会吹起太多碎片 损伤火星车
because the rockets will kick up too much debris and damage the rover
所以我们要用一条21英尺长的绳子缓缓把火星车降到火星表面
21英尺≈6.4米
so then we lower it from a 21-foot rope and gently land the rover on the surface
随后我的天空起重机将用其最后的燃料飞得越远越好 最终壮烈坠毁
as my skycrane zooms off to face an honorable catastrophic ending
as far away from the rover as its remaining fuel will carry it
短短七分钟 航天器就牺牲了外表所有零件
and so in just seven minutes the spacecraft has completely metamorphosized
shedding all its sacrificial elements
只剩一辆火星车 静静地安全地停在火星表面
until you're left with just a rover sitting alone safely on the surface of Mars
当然 你看到的一切画面都是CG动画
now everything you just saw was a CGI animation
av671781139
但着陆后几天 准备好吃惊吧
but a few days after landing we'll all be blown away
航天器上一共23个高清相机2个麦克风会传回画面
by actual HD landing footage from the 23 cameras and two microphones on board
我们会看到降落伞展开
we'll see the parachute inflate
听到火星车着陆时铝制车轮和火星表面接触的声音
and hear the crunch of the aluminum wheels as they touch down
and make contact with the martian surface
而因为火星离我们太远了
and because Mars is so far away
火星车到地球光速单程就要12分钟
to get a signal from the vehicle to our planet it takes about 12 minutes at the speed of light
这意味着 当航天器发出到达火星大气上层的信号
so that means after the spacecraft sends a signal that has reached the top of the atmosphere
然后信号传回地球 告诉我们恐怖七分钟已经开始了
by the time that signal reaches earth to kick off the seven minutes of tear
但此时已是火星车到达火星表面的五分钟后了 可能成功着陆 也可能失败坠毁
for at least five minutes the vehicle has actually already been on the surface either alive or dead
所以它必须是全自动的
which is why it has to be autonomous
它需要在各个时间点自行决策到底往哪飞
that means it makes all its own choices on the exact timing of things and where to steer
没有任何来自地球的控制
without anyone from earth controlling it
所有我们能做的 只有监看数据 默默祈祷
which means all we can do is watch and monitor and hope
其实这时大家才应该明白 工程师团队可能让这一些看起来很简单
and this is a good time to remember that as easy as these dedicated teams of engineers make it look
但着陆火星是真的相当难
landing on Mars is really hard
历史上只有一半的着陆尝试成功了
historically only about half the attempts have been successful
但愿意冒很大风险换来大的回报正是NASA建立的基础之所在
but the willingness to take big risks to reap big rewards is the foundation on which NASA is built
NASA全程直播回放：av586851624
着陆的直播将于2月18日周四 太平洋时间上午11点15开始
the live stream to watch the landing starts on Thursday Feb 18th at 11:15 am Pacific
一个半小时后 大约12点48分探测器到达大气上部
it will hit the top of the atmosphere an hour and a half later at 12:48 pm
开始恐怖七分钟 并在12点55分着陆
which starts to seven minutes of tear and we touch down at 12:55
我会在视频详情放直播链接
i will leave a link to the live stream in the video description
还有其他有趣的网页 比如这个像游戏一样的演示
as well as some other really cool sites such as this video-game-like demo
你可以在等候降落的时候和感受一下恐怖七分钟
where you can interactively experience the seven minutes of tear in preparation for the landing
我们讲了“去哪” 讲了“为什么去”
we covered the where and the why we're going
我们讲了“火星车怎么做” 以及“降落细节有什么”
we covered the how with the rover and the what with the landing details
该讲讲把火星车送到其他星球这件事背后的人了
now it's time for the who the human side to sending robot explorers to other planets
成就NASA和JPL的并不是造出来的机器 而是背后制造它的人
what makes NASA and JPL really great aren't its robots it's the people who build them
我可能没办法告诉大家他们到时候在周四会是怎样的感受
and while it's not really possible for me to capture
what it's gonna feel like for them to see at land this Thursday
而我能做的是告诉你们多年前我在类似情境下的感受
the best i can do is to show you what it felt like for me years ago
when i was in a very similar situation
我在好奇号着陆的时候做了一个视频 但当时频道粉丝还不到十万
i made a video when curiosity landed but at the time my channel had less than 100 000 subscribers
所以我知道你们很多人肯定没看过
so i know that most of you haven't seen this footage
但即使你们离这次着陆还有不到一周的时间
but even if you have with the landing less than a week away
我还是推荐你们去再看一次那个视频 给自己鼓鼓劲
it's a great time for a second watch to get you pumped up
我还希望大家知道我的情况 我当时在忙于火星车的工作
and for context here you should know that during my time i was working on the rover
ALS: 肌萎缩侧索硬化
在那期间我有了孩子 而我母亲因为ALS去世
i had a son and lost my mom to ALS
而尽管我的贡献可能相比整个项目微不足道
and while my contribution was small relative to the overall picture
我还是想抓住这里面的那份激情与感动
i tried to capture the human element here
你的人生与事业 整整七年奉献于此
of what it feels like to basically have seven years of your life and career
只为了等来那句最美的话：
vindicated with that beautiful phrase:
“确认着陆 我们安全到达火星！”
"Touchdown confirmed, we are safe on Mars!"
因此 我向每一位在这里工作的人致敬 是他们推进了人类求知的极限
so with that, consider this my tribute to everyone out there working to push the limits of human understanding
也感谢可爱的小Mark Rober的帮助~
with a little bit of help from adorable little young Mark Rober
着陆前2天
离着陆还有两天
so we're still two days from landing
但你们看 媒体的车早就来JPL这里了
but you see the news media has already started to descend on JPL here
我们最近都好紧张 所以这弄了个和以前不一样的赌池
since we're all kind of nervous around here, our office pools look a little different than most
这个椭圆是火星车预定着陆区范围
this is uh the landing ellipse for the rover
我们都在上面画好了自己猜测的着陆点
and we all kind of place guesses on where we think it's going to come down
我们正在和大家一同前往NASA JPL去看好奇号的着陆
着陆前2小时
真的超兴奋
甚至同时还有点反胃
我的人生 我的职业生涯里的七年就要浓缩在这七分钟里了
我好慌啊
着陆前30分钟
我欠那个人一半染色体~
这机会真棒啊
这机会不错吧？
我并不紧张
行吧
别怕 会成功的
着陆前10分钟
当Mark紧张的时候会表现得像很冷一样
其实现在气温能有30度呢 看把他给冻得~
Mark已经紧张坏了
真的是感慨万千啊
成功着陆火星后1分钟
图片传回来的时候 看到火星车的影子……
屹立在那 成为火星最强地标
想想都太牛逼了 你想想这可是我……
我设计的、摸过的、制造的、组装的、测试的东西
在另一个星球上安全着陆停稳了
简直了……
感觉太牛逼了
献给为让好奇号圆满完成任务而曾经共同做出贡献的3000多人
……也献给那些曾经给予他们动力的人
接下来是广告时间 不翻了